W. Landgon Kihn
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
W. Landgon Kihn papers
1904-1990, bulk 1904-1957
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Kihn, W. Langdon
8.5 linear feet
The papers of painter and illustrator W. Langdon Kihn measure approximately 8.5 linear feet and date from 1904-1990, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1904-1957. Papers document Kihn's career and travels associated with his interests in documenting the native American tribal nations of the United States and Canada in portraiture and writings. Found here are biographical materials, voluminous correspondence, memoirs and writings, one travel diary, printed material, financial records, three sketchbooks, sketches, and photographs.
Provenance
Helen Kihn, W. Langdon Kihn's widow, donated the bulk of the collection in 1959. In 1994 Phyllis Kihn, the artist's daughter, donated pages 1-8 of Kihn's original manuscript of his memoirs and a transcript of the complete memoirs.
Alternative Forms Available
The bulk of the collection is available on 35 mm microfilm reels 3701-3713 at Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the collection as described in this finding aid may not reflect the order of the collection on microfilm.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Born in Brooklyn, New York, W. (Wilfred) Langdon Kihn (1898-1959) is best known for his portraits of American Indians and illustrations of their history, culture and rapidly disappearing way of life. In 1919, Kihn joined his art teacher Winold Reiss on a trip to the Blackfeet Reservation in Montana where he completed his first series of portraits. This marked the beginning of his lifelong career of documenting the tribal nations of the United States and Canada. Through commissions from Canadian and American Railroad companies, Kihn spent much of the 1920s traversing both the United States and Northwest Canada where he had the opportunity to record the members and lives of various tribes. During this period, his paintings also traveled the country in a one man exhibition of his American Indian portraits, which was arranged by the Brooklyn Museum, and traveled to about 40 institutions in the United States. However his largest and best known commission was a project to research and paint North American Indians for serial publication in National Geographic. Kihn received the commission in 1935 and his association with the organization spanned two decades, culminating in the 1955 exhibition of his work at the National Geographic Museum, Washington, D.C, and the publication Indians of the Americas, with copius illustrations derived from Kihn's paintings and drawings.
In addition to his travels and work in North America, Kihn enjoyed a brief stint between 1929-1932 painting in France and Spain. Upon his return he focused upon obtaining commercial work and enjoyed success as an illustrator, whose work was featured in Beaver, Kings and Cabins (1933) and Flat Tail (1935), among other books. Kihn also wrote articles about his travels; amateur painters, whom he specialized in teaching; and American Indian legends and tribal cultures. Between 1948-1951 he was a partner in the Guy Wiggins-W. Langdon Kihn Art School in Essex, Connecticut. He married Helen Butler in 1920 and in between their travels the couple eventually settled in East Haddam, Connecticut. W. Langdon Kihn died in 1957.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of painter and illustrator W. Langdon Kihn measure approximately 8.5 linear feet and date from 1904-1990, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1904-1957. Papers document Kihn's career and travels associated with his interests in documenting the native American tribal nations of the United States and Canada in portraiture and writings. Found here are biographical material, voluminous correspondence, memoirs and writings, one travel diary, printed material, financial records, three sketchbooks, sketches, and photographs.
Biographical materials include address books, membership cards, exhibition and price lists, legal and travel documents, as well as biographical notes. Additional biographical sketches are found in the Writings and Notes series.
Correspondence is the largest series in the collection, almost half of the papers. In addition to letters to W. Langdon Kihn, this series include both originals and drafts of his outgoing letters; letters to his wife Helen from friends; third party business correspondence between his father, Alfred Kihn, and various parties undertaken on his son's behalf; and third party correspondence addressed to his friend and colleague, the Canadian ethnographer, Marius Barbeau. In addition to Barbeau, significant correspondents include Constance Lindsay Skinner, Chester and Maud Dale, Sir Henry Wellcome, Pierre and Marie "May" Lecompte du Noüy, and Reginald and Gladys Laubin. Although there is little correspondence with other artists, those represented with cards and letters in this collection include Boris Artzybasheff, Maynard Dixon, Olin Dows, Thornton Oakley, and Kihn's summer art school partner, Gus Wiggins. Correspondence with Franklin L. Fisher, Chief of National Geographic Magazine's Illustrated Division and Matthew W. Striling, Chief of the Bureau of American Ethnology at the Smithsonian Institution dominate the period spanning from 1935 - 1952, the years of Kihn's close association with the National Geographic Society.
Writings and notes includes manuscripts and typescripts of articles, poems, lectures, memoirs, and other writings by Kihn and others. There is one travel diary dated circa 1924-1925, and numerous writings about Kihn's travels and documentation of native American Indians.
Printed materials include exhibition catalogs, travel brochures, and magazine and newspaper clippings. Also found here are copies of Kihn's illustrations for books by other authors, including Beaver, Kings and Cabins, by Constance Lindsay Skinner, as well as proofs from the National Geographic series on American Indians arranged by geographic location. Financial records consist of invoices and receipts related to Kihn's artwork, traveling, and exhibitions.
Three sketchbooks and loose sketches include illustrated field notes and other drawings that document Kihn's travels and of native Americans. Photographs are of Kihn, and of Kihn at work. There are also photographs of Kihn's artwork.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 7 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1916-1957 (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1904-1959 (Boxes 1-5; 4.0 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, circa 1920-1990 (Box 5-6; 1.0 linear feet)
Series 4: Printed Material, circa 1920-1957 (Boxes 6-8, OV 10; 2.2 linear feet)
Series 5: Financial Records, 1920-1955 (Box 8; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 6: Sketchbooks and Sketches, circa 1922-1955 (Boxes 8-9, OV 10; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 7: Photographs, circa 1920-1955 (Box 9; 5 folders)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Book illustrators -- Connecticut; Indians of North America -- Pictorial Works; Painters -- Connecticut
Types of Materials:
Diaries; Photographs; Poetry; Sketches; Sketchbooks; Writings
Names:
Artzybasheff, Boris, 1899-1965; Barbeau, Marius, 1883-1969; Dale, Chester, b. 1883; Dale, Maud, 1875-1953; Dixon, Maynard, 1875-1946; Downs, Olin; Fisher, Franklin L.; Kihn, Alfred; Kihn, Helen Butler; Laubin, Gladys; Laubin, Reginald; Lecomte du Noüy, Marie; Lecomte du Noüy, Pierre, 1883-1947; Oakley, Thorton, 1881-1953; Skinner, Constance Lindsay, 1882-1939; Stirling, Matthew Williams, 1896-1975; Wellcome, Henry S. (Solomon), Sir, 1853-1936; Wiggins, Guy C. (Guy Carleton), 1883-1962
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Materials, circa 1916-1957, Series 1:; (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
  Biographical materials include address books, social cards, membership cards, biographical notes, exhibition lists, price lists, legal contracts, leases, insurance forms, and travel tickets and claim checks, which document Kihn's associates, work, and travel.
  Many of the biographical notes are drafts for entries in biographical encyclopedias. Additional biographical sketches and can be found in Writings and Notes.
  - Biographical Notes, before 1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Address Books, before 1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Address Book: Allied Brooklyn Artists Members, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Names and Addresses: Alaska, before 1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Loose Names and Addresses, circa 1920-1950, (social cards, envelopes, notes and lists) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Canadian Exhibition Price Lists and Notes, circa 1924 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Exhibition and Price Lists, circa 1922-1957, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
  - List of Works in the Collection of Edward Lyman Bill and Raymond Bill, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Inventory of Works by W. Langdon Kihn in the Kihn Estate, probably 1957 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Legal Documents, circa 1916-1955 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Membership Cards and Certificates, circa 1920-1952 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Tickets and Claim Checks, circa 1922-1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, circa 1904-1959, Series 2:; (Boxes 1-5, 4.0 linear feet)
  Personal and work-related correspondence is between Kihn and immediate family, close friends, and colleagues who shared his interest in American Indian culture. Kihn's outgoing correspondence is well-represented through handwritten drafts and carbon copies. Although the bulk of the incoming correspondence is addressed to Kihn, letters from mutual friends addressed to his wife Helen are scattered thoughout both the personal and chronological correspondence.
  The Correspondence series is arranged into 2 subseries:
  2.1: General and Personal Correspondence, circa 1916-1957
  2.2: Chronological Correspondence, 1904-1959
  - General and Personal Correspondence, circa 1916-1957, 2.1:
    This subseries consists primarily of personal correspondence, including holiday cards and invitations, although letters related to commissions and exhibitions are scattered throughout.
    This subseries includes the letters of W. Langdon Kihn, Alfred and Carrie Kihn (his parents), and Helen Kihn (his wife). Langdon Kihn's correspondence contains letters to his parents from his early trips out west, and drafts and fragments of letters to colleagues promoting his early exhibitions. There is also a selection of Christmas cards of his own design, which he sent to friends and family.
    Notable correspondents, most of whom are also represented in the chronological correspondence, include the Canadian ethnographer, Marius Barbeau; well-known collectors, Dale and Maud Chester and Sir Henry Wellcome; artists Maynard Dixon and Guy Wiggins; French biophysicist and philosopher Pierre du Noüy; and military historian Captian Russell V. Steele, whose letters frequently include illustrations of soldiers in military uniforms.
    Folders are arranged in alphabetical order by correspondent name. Letters and letter fragments with missing or illegible signatures have been filed in a folder titled "Unidentified," which is located at the end of this subseries.
    - General A, circa 1922-1950 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Adams, C.
      Adams, J Donald
      Adams, Mrs. John Adams
      Ament, Robert. S.
      American Indian Defense Association
      Armer, Ruth
      Armer, Sidney
      Armstead, George Brooks
      Arnaud, Odette
      Artic Institute of North America
      Artzybasheff, Boris and Elizabeth
      Austrain, H.
    - Bosworth, Tom, circa 1928-1930 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - General Ba-Boo, circa 1922-1950 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Barbona, Ruth
      Barbeau, Marius
      Batchelor, J
      Beau, Henri
      Beck, Charles W. Jr.
      Bernet-Rollande, L.
      Bill, Edward Lyman
      Black Hawk
      Blassingame, Lurton
      Bogree, Jane
      Booth, Mr. and Mrs. John R. Jr.
    - General Bow-By, before 1957 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Bowen, Catherine Drinker
      Bowles, Dorothy and Chester
      Bray, Muriel
      Brooklyn Children's Museum
      Brown, Sonia Gordon
      Budlong, Mary
      Butler, Margaret
      Butler, William
      Bye, George T.
    - General C, before 1957 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Cadmen, Benaldine Noble
      Cappius, E.
      Cartier, Jacques
      Caspanu [?], Millicent
      Caskey, James F.
      Charles Scribner's Sons
      Chase, ?
      Church, Esther
      Clark, Allan
      Clark, Joy
      Clark, Margery
      Clark, Mary Moore
      Coburn, Mary
      Continental Theater
      Cookingham, Louise K.
      Courtright, George and Eugenie
      Crago, W. H.
      Crussaire, Dr. and Mme.
    - General D, 1916, before 1957 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      D., Myrtle
      Dale, Maud and Chester
      De Bogory, Natalie
      DeLeon, Bertha
      Dixon, Maynard
      Doolittle, Mary F.
      Dow, Emily K.
      Driemeyer, Betty
      Dudley, Lillian
    - General E-F, before 1957 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Eastern Association of Indian Affairs
      Eaton, Earle Hooker
      Emery, Roe
      Ennis, Howard Jr.
      Explorers Club
      F., E.
      First Unitarian Church of Philadelphia
      Fisher, Franklin
      Fitzpatrick, Lee ("Fitz")
      Flandrau, Grace
    - General G, before 1957 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Gallup, Anna Billings
      Galvin, Bob
      Gates, Allen H.
      Gatewood, Bill
      Gaultier de la Verendrye, Juliette
      Gaza, Maria Josepha
      Gibbs, A. Hamilton
      Gibbs, Jeanette
      Gliewe, Ramon
      Goismsditch, Herbert B.
      Goulding, Margaret
      Gray, Fred
      Green, W.W. and LuLu
      Griffiths, Nellie
      Griswold, Charlotte B.
      Grosso, Alfonso
      Grosvenor, Mr. And Mrs. Gilbert
    - General H, before 1957 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Hamilton, Margaret
      Hanson, Earl P.
      Hartford Courant
      Hartford Times
      Harris, Walter A.
      Hartman, Jennette (Mrs. E.R.)
      Harper and Brothers
      Hewitt, E. L.
      Hill, Mr. and Mrs. Louis W.
      Hinton, Harold B.
      Holden, Frances
      Holden, Lephe
      Hopkins, Ellen
      Hutchinson, Dorothy and James
      Hutchinson, George
    - General J-L, circa 1920-1957 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      James, Will
      Jason, T.
      Keithahn, Edward and Marie Antoinette ("Nette")
      Kirk, Ruth (Mrs. John)
      Lasker, Bruno
      Laubin, Reginald ("Redge") and Gladys
      Lay, Charles D.
      Leechman, Douglas
      Lomen, Laura and Carl
      Longheed, Sir James
      Lowry, Royal
      Lummis, Charles F.
      Lyme Minute Men
    - Kihn, Alfred C. and Carrie, before 1957 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Kihn, Helen, circa 1920-1957 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Kihn, W. Langdon, circa 1920-1957 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Lecompte du Noüy, Pierre and Marie (May), circa 1927-1947, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 28-29)
    - General M-N, circa 1920-1957 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      MacMillan Company
      Mallory, Lenore
      Manfred, Ernest
      Marsh, ?
      Mason, Charles and Rose
      Matthias, Reva
      McDonald, E.
      Meistrell, Malcom
      Morden, William and Florence
      Morse, Harry
      N., Frances
      National Gallery of Art, Washington DC
      National Geographic Society
      Newberry, Mary
      Newsom, William ("Bill")
      Niven, Pauline and Frederick
    - General O-R, circa 1920-1957 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      O'Neil, Henry
      Paisano, Ulysses G. Sr.
      Parsons, Sheldon
      Pond, James B.
      Post, Landgon
      Price, Fred
      Raynolds, Ellen
      Reid, Russell
      Reiss, Henrietta
      Remington, Beatrice
      Rindge, Dottie
      Rosen, Elsie
      Rungins, Carl
    - Skinner, Constance Lindsay, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Steele, Captain Russell V., circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - General S, circa 1920-1957 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      Salmagundi Club
      Sawyer, Fannette
      Schellbach, Don
      Scott, Duncan Cambell
      Seaman, Joseph H.
      Shapiro, H.L.
      Smith, Theodora
      Soper, Mr. and Mrs. Ellis
      Speer, Ella Post
      Staats-Herold Corporation
      Stevens, Harry
      Stirling, Matt and Marion
    - General T-V, circa 1920-1957 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      Taber-Prang Co.
      Taylor, Cecilia E and H. Peach
      Thomas, Virginia
      Tillon, Edith
      Tompkins, V.
      Treasury Department, Section of Painting and Sculpture
      Tremaine, Mr. and Mrs. Burton
      Trujillo, Mrs. M. H.
      Tucker, Patricia
      Tyler, Flora C.
      Tyler, Gertrude
      Voorhees, Aimée
    - Wiggins, Guy, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - General W-Z, circa 1920-1957 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      W., Jess
      Washburn, Tahoe and Linc
      Watson, Mr. and Mrs. Edwin
      Watson, Elmo Scott
      Weems, Carrington
      Wellcome, Sir Henry
      White, Catherine F.
      White, Peter
      Whitney, Carol
      Women's Day
      Zeusler
    - Unidentified, before 1957 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Chronological Correspondence, circa 1917-1959, 2.2:
    Found in this subseries are letters to and from Kihn that document his career as an artist, illustrator, teacher, and writer. Scattered through out are personal correspondence, including letters addressed to his wife Helen from their mutual friends. There is also a cache of third party correspondence addressed to Marius Barbeau, a Canadian ethnologist who was a colleague and friend of Kihn's.
    The earliest correspondence includes letters from his parents, particularly his father Alfred Kihn, who also trained as an artist and founded a steel engraving firm with his brother that specialized in bank note engraving. Kihn senior not only wrote proffering career advice, but also corresponded with his son's business and personal associates while Langdon Kihn was on extended trips. There are also letters from W. Langdon Kihn to his parents describing his trips, including his impressions of San Francisco, Glacier Park, experiences painting Indian portraits, as well as his 1929-1932 sojourn painting in Paris and Spain. These early letters also record exhibitions, primarily a traveling exhibition of his portraits of members of the Blackfeet Indian tribe, which was organized by the Brooklyn Museum of Art and traveled to over 40 institutions in the United States.
    Letters to and from authors, publishers, advertisers, and collectors comprise a large amount of correspondence from late 1920s to the mid 1930s, which document his efforts at securing commissions for commercial work. During this time he also began to submit articles about his work and travels. Correspondents include the author Constance Lindsay Skinner; publishers Macmillan and Company; Little, Brown, and Company; Harcourt Brace and Company; and magazines including, Fortune and Story Parade.
    The bulk of the chronological correspondence records his association with the National Geographic magazine, spanning from 1935-1955. The National Geographic Society commissioned Kihn to paint historical and contemporary scenes of the lives of over 35 tribal nations from the continental United States, Alaska, and the Northwest Territories. Engraved illustrations of his paintings were published in the magazine's ongoing series on American Indians between 1937 and 1949. Most of the related correspondence was between Kihn, Franklin L. Fisher, Chief of National Geographic's Illustrated Division and Matthew W. Striling, Chief of the Bureau of American Ethnology at the Smithsonian Institution, who also played an important role in this project.
    Letters have been arranged in folders in chronological order. However, there are examples of early correspondence in which the original letter and the later response letter have been glued together. No attempt has been made to separate them and in some cases they may disrupt the chronological arrangement.
    See Index to Series 2.2: Chronological Correspondence, circa 1917-1959 for a select list of individuals and organizations represented here.
    - Correspondence, 1904-1916 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Correspondence, 1917-1919 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Correspondence, 1920 January-August (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Correspondence, 1920 September-December (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Correspondence, 1921 January-May (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Correspondence, 1921 June-December (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Correspondence, 1922 January-April (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Correspondence, 1922 May (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Correspondence, 1922 June (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Correspondence, 1922 July (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Correspondence, 1922 August (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Correspondence, 1922 September (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Correspondence, 1922 October (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Correspondence, 1922 November-December (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Correspondence, 1923 January-February (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Correspondence, 1923 March-April (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1923 May-June (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1923 July-September (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1923 October-November (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1923 December (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1924 January-February (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1924 March-May (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1924 June (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1924 July-August (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1924 September-October (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1924 November-December (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1925 January-February (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1925 March-May (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1925 June-December (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1926 January-April (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, 1926 May-June (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, 1926 July-August (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, 1926 September-October (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, 1926 November-December (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, 1927 January-April (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, 1927 May-December (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence, 1928 January-March (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence, 1928 April-December (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence, 1929 January-May (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence, 1929 June-December (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence, 1930 January-February (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence, 1930 March-April (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence, 1930 May-August (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence, 1930 September-December (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence, 1931 January-July (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence, 1931 August-December (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence, 1932 January-June (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence, 1932 July-December (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence, 1933 January-June (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence, 1933 July-December (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1934 January-August (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1934 September-December (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1935 January-April (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1935 May-September (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1935 October-December (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1936 January-February (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1936 March-July (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1936 August-December (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, circa 1937 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1937 January-May (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1937 June-July (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1937 August-December (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1938 January-June (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1938 July-December (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, 1939 January-March (Box 3, Folder 16)